

ASTRONOMER

INAF - Astronomical Observatory of Trieste, Via Giambattista Tiepolo, 11, 34131, Trieste, Italy

□ (+39) 351-946-0362 | ■ louise.amber.welsh@gmail.com | ★ lawelsh.github.io | 匝 Louise Welsh | ● 0000-0003-3174-7054

Summary _____

In my research, I study chemical evolution across cosmic time as well as the first stars and galaxies. Primarily, I use the largest optical telescopes in the world to study some of the least chemically evolved gas 2 billion years after the Big Bang. The gas clouds are encoded with information about their star formation history and can, in combination with a chemical enrichment model that I have developed, reveal the mass distribution of ancient stellar populations. This information is invaluable because the properties of the first stellar populations are still shrouded in mystery. This work is possible through a process known as quasar absorption line spectroscopy – where gas between a bright background galaxy and our telescope can be seen, and subsequently studied, in absorption. This field will soon be revolutionised thanks to upcoming spectroscopic surveys that will produce datasets of unprecedented quality and scope. Furthermore, in the next decade, we will see the advent of the next generation of ground-based telescopes with apertures 3 times greater than the current state-of-the-art. My current research is focused on maximally utilising these technological advances to reveal the properties of the first stars. This research is essential to understand the first instances of chemical enrichment and galaxy formation in the early Universe.

Employment

INAF Astronomical Observatory of Trieste

Trieste, Italy

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER Sep. 2023 - PRESENT

University of Milano Bicocca

Milan, Italy

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER

Sep. 2021 - Sep. 2023

Education

Centre for Extragalactic Astronomy, Durham University

Durham, UK

PhD in Astrophysics

Oct. 2017 - Sep. 2021

- Thesis: 'A window to the first stars: An investigation of chemically near-pristine environments'
- · Advisor: Prof. Ryan Cooke

Lancaster UniversityMASTER OF PHYSICS (MPHYS): 1st CLASS (HONS)

Lancaster, UK

Oct. 2012 - Jul. 2016

- Thesis: 'Investigating cold dark matter candidates'
- Advisor: Dr. John McDonald

Awards and Fellowships _____

2021	Keith Nicholas Prize , Awarded for outstanding overall performance by a postgraduate student.	Durham University

Associate Fellow of the Higher Education Academy, through the Durham Excellence in Learning and Teaching Awards scheme.

2019 Martin and Beate Block Award, Awarded to a promising researcher at the Aspen winter meeting 'Into the Aspen Centre for Starlight'.

Aspen Centre for Physics

2016 **Azzedine Hammiche Prize**, Awarded for exceptional fourth year project work. *Lancaster University*

Talks (6 invited, 29 total)

Most recent:

OCTOBER 11, 2023

Sep. 2023 Spectral Fidelity, The metal-poor Universe (invited)	Italy
July 2022 Habitable Worlds Near prictipe DLAss A window to the first stars	STScI

July. 2023 **Habitable Worlds**, Near pristine DLAs: A window to the first stars

May. 2023 **IFPU First Stars**, The most metal-poor DLAs as a window to the first stars (invited)

April 2023 Wine & Cheese seminar, Oxygen-enhanced extremely metal-poor DLAs

April 2023 Galaxy journal club, The most metal-poor DLAs as a window to the first stars

STScI

LOUISE WELSH · CURRICULUM VITÆ

Proposal History as Principle Investigator _____

2023	VLT/ESPRESSO 4-UT, 1.2 nights, P112.	ESO
2023	VLT/UVES, 10 hours, P111.	ESO
2023	Keck I/HIRES, 1 night, 2023A.	NOIRLab
2022	VLT/UVES, 10 hours, P110.	ESO
2022	VLT/ESPRESSO 1-UT, 7 hours, P109.	ESO
2022	VLT/ESPRESSO 3-UT, 8 hours, P109.	ESO
2021	VLT/UVES, 18 hours, P108.	ESO
2021	Keck I/HIRES, 1 night, 2021B.	NOIRLab
2020	VLT/ESPRESSO 1-UT, 9 hours, P105.	ESO
2020	VLT/UVES, 20 hours, P105.	ESO
2019	WHT/ISIS, 7 nights, 2019B.	ING

Proposal History as Primary Scientific Investigator ______

2023	WEAVE/LIFU, 21 hours, 2023B.	UK PATT
2020	Palomar/Hale, 7 night, 2020A.	Caltech

Teaching _____

2023 Advisor , Student bachelor thesis in physics	Milano-Bicocca U.
2022 - 2023 Demonstrator , Laboratory of Data Acquisition (postgraduate course)	Milano-Bicocca U.
2021 Advisor , Nuffield Research Placement	Durham University
2019 - 2021 Demonstrator , Level 2: Stars and Galaxies	
2018 - 2020 Demonstrator , Level 1: Further Mathematics for Geoscientists	
2018 - 2019 Demonstrator , Level 1: Maths toolkit for Scientists	

Memberships and activities _____

- 2023 **WEAVE**, IFU Working Group Member for WEAVE QSO survey.
- 2022 **WMAG 2022**, Organising committee member for the 'What Matters around Galaxies 2022' conference.
- 2022 **Peer reviewer**, MNRAS.
- 2021 **WEAVE**, Member of the WEAVE-QSO survey.
- 2021 **Peer reviewer**, Astrophysical Journal.
- 2021 **Astrocoffee**, Organiser of weekly astrocoffee seminars at Milano-Bicocca.
- 2021 **INAF**, Associate member of INAF Osservatorio Astronomico di Brera.
- 2020 2021 **OCW social**, Member of committee responsible for organising department social events.
 - 2020 **DEX XVI**, LOC member for the '2020 Vision: progress and tensions in astronomy' workshop.
 - 2019 **Small Galaxies, Cosmic Questions**, LOC member for the 'Small Galaxies, Cosmic Questions' conference.
- 2018 2019 Journal Club, Convener of a weekly meeting of postgraduate students at Durham University.

Outreach_

Planetarium North East, UK

 Show provider
 Oct. 2018 - Sep. 2020

Delivered shows on the constellations and planets at events (including multiple science festivals) and local schools using an inflatable planetarium.

Computing Skills _____

Programming Python, git, high-performance computing, batch systems, RStudio.

Publications

- L. Welsh, R. Cooke, M. Fumagalli, & M. Pettini (2023) "Towards ultra metal-poor DLAs: linking the chemistry of the most metal-poor DLA to the first stars", MNRAS, 525, 527
- Longobardi et al. (2023) "Towards an automatic approach to modelling the circumgalactic medium: new tools for mock making and fitting of metal profiles in large surveys", RASTI, 2, 470
- R. Cooke et al. (2022) "Primordial helium-3 redux: The helium isotope ratio of the Orion nebula", ApJ, 932, 60
- L. Welsh, R. Cooke, M. Fumagalli, & M. Pettini (2022) "Oxygen-enhanced EMP DLAs: A signpost of the first stars?", ApJ, 929, 158
- L. Welsh, R. Cooke, & M. Fumagalli (2021) "The stochastic enrichment of Population II stars", MNRAS, 500, 5214
- R. Cooke, L. Welsh, M. Fumagalli, & M. Pettini (2020) "A limit on Planck-scale froth with ESPRESSO", MNRAS, 494, 4884
- L. Welsh, R. Cooke, M. Fumagalli, & M. Pettini (2020) "A bound on the 12 C/ 13 C ratio in near-pristine gas with ESPRESSO", MNRAS, 494, 1411
- L. Welsh, R. Cooke, & M. Fumagalli (2019) "Modelling the chemical enrichment of Population III supernovae: the origin of the metals in near-pristine gas clouds", MNRAS, 487, 3363

My ADS publication library can be found here: https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/public-libraries/X39_5pqERBKF3J023SYKRA.